<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of an imposition layed by the late king upon the manufactures of gold &amp; silver-wyer to be used in the making of gold &amp; silver thred, &amp;c. : Which was voted by the grand Committee of Parliament to be a monopoly. / Written by one that was well acquainted with all the proceedings. ; Published by D.T. a lover of truth.</title>
            <author>D. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95573</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789423</idno>
  <idno type="VID">172733</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240887508</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing T4D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187459</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">45789423</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2647:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of an imposition layed by the late king upon the manufactures of gold &amp; silver-wyer to be used in the making of gold &amp; silver thred, &amp;c. : Which was voted by the grand Committee of Parliament to be a monopoly. / Written by one that was well acquainted with all the proceedings. ; Published by D.T. a lover of truth.</title>
                  <author>D. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.C. and are to be sold at the Fountaine in Goldsmiths-row in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Pennsylvania. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  Honorable the Grand Committee for Trade.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Filigree --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Trade regulation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172733:1"/>
            <p>A true Relation of an IMPOSITION LAYED BY THE LATE KING UPON THE MANUFACTURES OF GOLD &amp; SILVER-WYER To be used in the making of GOLD &amp; SILVER THRED, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which was voted by the grand Committee of Parliament to be a Monopoly.</p>
            <p>Written by one that was well acquainted with all the proceedings.</p>
            <p>Published by <hi>D.T.</hi> a lover of truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> and are to be sold at the Fountaine in Goldsmiths-row in Cheapside, 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172733:2"/>
            <head>A true Relation of an imposition layed by the late King upon the manufactures of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Wyer to be used in the making of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thred, &amp;c. which was voted by the Grand Committee of Parliament to be a monopoly.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the comming of <hi>King James</hi> to the Crown the wearing of Gold and Silver Lace in <hi>Englan<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath been much encreased, by reason whereo<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the number of Gold Wyer drawers in an<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about the City of <hi>London,</hi> to fit and prepar<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gold and Silver thred for the making thereof, have multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed also; which were not incorporated into one Society but promiscuously joyned to several other Societies of th<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> said City; By reason whereof, they had no Charter to enab<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> them to regulate the said Trade among themselves, nor t<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> suppresse any others from exercising the same, who neve<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> served as Apprentices thereunto; for want whereof ma<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of other professions betooke themselves unto the workin<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and making of the said manufactures, as well as those whos<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proper Trade it was; and so became sharers in the profi<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> thereof, to the great discontent of the said Gold-Wye<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> drawers; which persons so intruding they called Interloper<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> For the suppressing of whom, many of the chiefe of the sa<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Gold-wyer-drawers, applyed themselves to one <hi>Mr. Tomki<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Mr. Leake</hi> Sollicitors, and Sergeant <hi>Whitfield</hi> of Counc<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to the then Lord of <hi>Holland,</hi> to procure the said Lord<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172733:3"/>mediate with the <hi>King</hi> to make them a Corporation, and after many consultations had to that purpose, they came to an agreement; and in pursuance thereof, and for the better effecting of their desires, they subscribed a Petition to the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate <hi>King Charles,</hi> and procured it to be delivered by Sir <hi>Ralph Freeman</hi> one of the Masters of the Requests, in <hi>April,</hi> 1635. In which Petition they pray, <hi>That they, and such others as have served in the said Arts or Trades, or such as your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners shall deeme fit to use the same, and one or two Finers that may fine Gold and Silver, to be used in the aforesaid Trades, with a</hi> non <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bstante, the Statute of 4 Hen. 7th. <hi>or any other</hi> Statute <hi>or</hi> Proclamation <hi>may be incorporated into a body Politique, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of a Master, two Wardens, twelve Assistants, and Commonalty, and thereby have power, to bring all the parties of the said Arts and Trades into order, and Purchase an Hall for their Company and make Orders and by Laws for the better regulating and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the said Company, and raising of the moneys to be reserved <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors by their Charter, and for <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll necessary charges for driving and maintaining their Trades, <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that no Gold or Silver thred, or Copper Gold and Silver thred may be put to sale, unlesse it be sealed with the seal of the said <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ompany, and to have such liberties and priviledges as may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance the Trades. And that Corporation for his Majesties grace <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd goodnesse to them, in continuing their Trades, and reducing the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to Government; humbly offer to render and pay to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esty, his Heirs and Successors for ever, One thousand and pounds yearly, <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom</hi> Michaelmas <hi>then next, and for and towards the provision <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd importation of such Bulloign and Species, as the members of <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he said Corporation shall use in the said manufacture, would also <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay unto his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, two pence for every <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unce of the said Bulloign and foraign Species, which should be used <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y them in the said Trades, over and above the currant price of the Merchants, &amp;c. And that his Majesty would be pleased to publish <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s Royall Proclamation, thereby declaring his Royall will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172733:4"/>to be, that no person or persons whatsoever, within his Majesties Kingdome, do practice or use any of the said Arts, Trades, Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or drawing &amp; spinning of Gold and Silver thred, other then such as should be incorporated and admitted into the Petitioners Society.</hi> Which Petition of theirs was seconded by a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord of <hi>Holland;</hi> the Contents whereof followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Kings most excellent Majesty: The humble Petition of</hi> Henry <hi>Earle of</hi> Holland. <hi>Shewing,</hi> That your Majesty, some years since, did grant unto your Petitioner the power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate and govern the manufactures of Gold and Silver thred, with a Relation to a former grant made unto him, of your Majesties exchange, was then thought fittest to be done by way of Licence or faculty; But that nothing being done upon that grant, which passed no further then the privy Seal, your Petitioner considering the increase of the said Trades, with the abuses thereof, hath treated with the Gold Wyer-drawers, and findeth that the Reglement thereof by way of incorporation, agreeth best with the nature of the businesse, and their desires: who humbly offer unto <hi>your Majesty</hi> for your grace and goodnesse to them, in continuing of their Trades, and reducing the same to Government, to pay to your Majesty, from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> next for ever, One thousand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and two pence upon every ounce of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loign &amp; forraign Species, which shal be used by them in their manufactures, for and towards the provision and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, which offers they have been invited thereunto, by your Petitioners great labour and expences; he humbly tendreth to your Majesties consideration, with his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble suit that your Majesty would be graciously pleased, in accomplishment of your royal favour long since intended to him in this particuler, to grant to your Petitioner a Lease of the said thousand pounds, and of the two pence for provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and importation of Bulloign as aforesaid, for the term of one and thirty years, from <hi>Michaelmas</hi> next, and your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172733:5"/>Petitioner will provide a Merchant or Merchants who shall yearly serve the said Company, with as much Bulloyne and Forreign species, as they shall use in their said Trades, and after the said one and thirty years ended, the whole Benefit of the Reservations by the Patent of Incorporation, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main as a constant Revenue to <hi>your Majesty</hi> and your Heirs for ever. And the Petitioner will ever pray for your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties long life. Both which Petitions were referred to Mr. Attorney General to take into Consideration, the Request of the Goldwyer-drawers; and to hear the Councel and Agents of the Petitioners, and to certifie his <hi>Majesty</hi> whether the Corporation desired be a fit means to regulate the said Trades, and upon what Conditions and Priviledges, the same might be passed, for the best advantage of his Majesties Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the publique Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where observe,</hi> That the said Corporation of the Wyer-drawers, and the powers thereof in their Petition desired would (if granted) have suppressed all the Refiners from the exercise of their ancient Trade, (except one or two whom they would have taken in to fine Gold and Silver to be used in their said trades.) Now whilst this Businesse of the Wyer-drawers was agitating by them, with the persons aforenamed There was one <hi>Henry Ockald</hi> did offer to sell an Jugot of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in weight about three and forty Ounces, to Mr. <hi>Ralph La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thum</hi> a Goldsmith in <hi>Cheapside,</hi> who stayed the same upon sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition that it was not lawfuly come by, which Jugot was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards carried to the Master of the Kings Jewel-house, &amp; the said <hi>Ockald</hi> (examined by the Lord chief Justice <hi>Richardson</hi>) said, he was sent by one <hi>Philips</hi> a brother in Law of his to sell the same to Mr. <hi>John Wollaston</hi> in <hi>Foster</hi>-lane, to whom he had formerly sold <hi>Spanish</hi> Silver, for another brother in Law of his one <hi>Jermin Honychurch.</hi> Whereupon the said Mr. <hi>Wollaston</hi> was also examined, and denied that he had any acquaintance with the said <hi>Philips,</hi> or had formerly bought any Silver of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172733:6"/>him but said, that he did ordinarily, buy Jugots, and other parcels of molten Gold and Silver, of Merchants and Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths. Hereupon <hi>S. H. M.</hi> encouraged the Goldsmiths in <hi>Cheapside,</hi> to Petition <hi>the King</hi> for a Remedy of their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and in case they would give a charge against the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finers, he would further their Petition, which accordingly they did upon his encouragement, and in the first Article of that Petition set forth, <hi>That divers persons and trades-men, as well in the City of</hi> London, <hi>and the suburbs thereof, as in divers other parts of the Kingdome, did deal and intermedle in their said trade, and the wares and commodities solely and properly appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to it, which were never bred nor served as Apprentices to the same, and sundry Mercers and petty chapmen in the Country, did buy great quantities of Plate, burnt-Silver, and other Goldsmiths commodities, and returned them to</hi> London <hi>to other tradesmen, that they dealt withall, who sold the same againe to the Finers at their private houses, whereby the Petitioners were not only hindred in their trade, but also the Commonwealth suffered by it, in regard that by this means it was probable, that stolen wares were bought and sold, and could never be discovered, which might be done if they were sold in open Market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Second Article they complain, of Brokers lending money upon Plate and other Goldsmiths Wares, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the finding out of stolen Goods.</p>
            <p>In the Third Article they complain, that some in the old and new Exchange, &amp;c. sold Goldsmiths wares, made of course Gold and Silver, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And in the fourth ARticle they complain, of divers of their own profession, that disperst themselves into several pa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, in and about the City, inlarged their Shops, and ingrossed almost all the whole trade, whereby the generality of the Company were exceedingly impoverished, and then pray the King to prevent these inconveniences, touching their said trade, for the good of the Kingdome in general, and the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners in special, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172733:7"/>
            <p> Observe here, <hi>That as the Gold wyer-drawers would have the Refiners suppressed from</hi> selling; <hi>so these Petitioners would have them restrained from</hi> buying, <hi>which were both hard Petitions in that respect, and had both their success accordingly. Ʋpon this Petition, seconded with a Complaint of</hi> S.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.H.M. <hi>to the</hi> King <hi>and his</hi> Council, <hi>As is inserted in the preamble of an Order thereupon made, which Order was to this effect,</hi> That <hi>S. H. M.</hi> should go to Mr. Attorney General with his dispositions, &amp;c. and that the Goldsmiths should likewise attend the said Mr. Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, with such Informations as they had or could recover by further inquiery, and that thereupon Mr. <hi>Attorney</hi> should prosecute in a legall way, such as he should find to be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (as well Goldsmiths as Refiners) and cause the Statute of 4. <hi>Henry 7th</hi> to be strictly put in Execution, and such course to be presently taken, that the penalties thereupon should be recovered against such, as were or should be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders against the said Statute. <hi>These Allegations being to weak for Mr. Attorney to ground any information upon the said</hi> S.H. M. <hi>procured a Commission under the great Seal</hi> dated the Seventh day of <hi>April</hi> in the 11th year of the said King <hi>for him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers therein named;</hi> to enquire into the abuses committed by Goldsmiths, Finers of Gold and Silver, Disgrossers of Gold and Silver, and by Wyer drawers, Silkmen and others in the buying and selling of Gold and Silver, of and to divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of several professions, and in not bringing the same unto the <hi>Mint, Exchanges and Goldsmiths</hi> for augmentation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of Coin and Plate, as they ought to have done, but convert the same to the making of Silver thred, Spangles and Oaes, and such like unnecessary things, and buying of Plate oft times stoln from <hi>his Majesty</hi> and his Subjects, either in Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or in Masse molten, and for exporting of Gold and Silver out of the Realm, by vertue of which <hi>Commission</hi> the said <hi>S. H. M.</hi> and other <hi>Commissioners</hi> proceeded in the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of many persons of the several professions aforesaid,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172733:8"/>and of their Servants, Workmen, and such as bought and sold with them, and did thereby and also by imploying his Agents to buy small parcels, of such as were suspected to work and sell course and fraudulent Wares, discover several parcels of Silver and Gold Lace, mingled with Copper and made much worse then the Standard, in the hands of seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Silkmen, and other course Silver-wyer cast with a Core of Copper, which deceit had been practized by one <hi>Heyward</hi> a Refiner and one <hi>Gare</hi> (formerly a Silkman and afterwards turned) Wyer-drawer, and also course Spangles and Plate in the hands of Spangle-makers; yet amongst the multitude of his and their Examinations, they neither did nor could discover any Refiner to have bought any stolen Plate in Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or Molten into Masse, or otherwise; or any of the currant money of the Kingdom melted down, or any Gold or Silver transported beyond the Seas, or any Silver sold by them worse then Standard, or any other fraudulent and deceitful dealing, in any of the particulars mentioned in his <hi>Commission,</hi> practised by any of the Refiners, excepting the aforesaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit committed by the said <hi>Heyward;</hi> but onely that they had bought quantities of Silver and Gold, in their own houses, of Merchants and Goldsmiths at the currant prices of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket; part whereof they had refined, and sold to Goldwyer-drawers, (which time out of mind was their proper trade) to be used in the aforesaid manufactures, and allowed to be worn by the <hi>King, Nobility, and Gentry</hi> of the Nation, and other part thereof they fitted and sold to the Plate working Goldsmiths, for making of Plate, and to the <hi>Minte</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of moneys. And about the time wherein all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars afore mentioned were transacting, one Mr. <hi>Thomas Violet</hi> (a shop keeping Goldsmith in <hi>Lumbardstreet</hi>) was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and imprisoned by warrant from Secretary <hi>Cook,</hi> for transporting quantities of Gold beyond the Seas; who being examined before a Baron of the Exchequer did (first
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172733:9"/>deny, but afterwards) confesse the said offence; and in order to the procuring of his pardon for the same, did not only disburse <hi>great summs of money,</hi> but also engaged to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver twenty other persons to be guilty of some or other of the offences mentioned in the aforesaid Commission, and to prosecute them <hi>in the Star-Chamber</hi> to a conviction, that the King might have their Fines; and for the effecting thereof, drew a Bill, which was exhibited in the said <hi>Court</hi> in the name of the then <hi>Attorney Generall;</hi> in which <hi>Bill</hi> were inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the names of divers Merchants, Goldsmiths, and Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and thereupon, and by vertue of a warrant from Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Cook,</hi> a Pursevant was imployed, who did apprehend and imprison the persons, and seize the Books and papers of severall Merchants and Trades men, whereof Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> was one, whose Counting-house and Study was sealed up, and his person imprisoned several days; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could be released, was constrained to enter into a Bond of five thousand pounds penalty, to appear at the Councel-board at three dayes warning. In the prosecution of which business, the said Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> became so active &amp; dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that a stop was put to the Gold Wyer-drawers Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to <hi>S.H.M.</hi> his further proceedings upon his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission;</hi> and another way <hi>resolved upon</hi> for the Regulating of the Trades of Refiners and Gold Wyer-drawers, and for the raising and imposing of six pence an ounce upon all Gold and Silver Wyer, that should be used in the aforesaid manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures: And for the effecting thereof, the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> and <hi>Alderman Gibs</hi> Refiners, and many of the Gold Wyer-drawers, were summoned to the Councel-Table; and there the <hi>King</hi> demanded, whether they would volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily submit to the payment of the said six pence, and such further Regulation of their Trades as he should appoint for the future; but none of the persons, neither Refiners nor Gold Wyer-drawers, then present, yielded thereunto; but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172733:10"/>some of them alledged, that it was a greater imposition then the commodity would bear; and one of the Wyer-drawers answered, that they would submit to the Laws. Yet the <hi>King</hi> to make a further tryal, said, <hi>those that will sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, go to my right hand;</hi> and <hi>those that will not, go to my left;</hi> and again said, <hi>the sheep to my right hand,</hi> and <hi>the goats to the left;</hi> but neither the Refiners nor Gold Wyer-drawers stirred from their places, neither did the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> or Alderman <hi>Gibs,</hi> offer either six pence, or any other Taxe to be imposed upon the said commodity, and so they were difmissed. And shortly after the said Refiners were attached by a Pursevant, and to avoid imprisonment were constrained to enter into <hi>Bonds</hi> of five hundred pounds a piece, to desist from the exercise of their Trade till further Order; and soon after, the Refiners and Gold Wyer-drawers were often summoned to the <hi>Attorney General</hi>'s Chamber, and once or twice some of the Silk-men were summoned thither also, before Sir <hi>John Bankes</hi> the said <hi>Attorney General,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Sollicitor, Litleton,</hi> Mr. Sergeant <hi>Whitfield,</hi> and others of my Lord of <hi>Holland</hi>'s Councel, &amp; <hi>S.H.M.</hi> and several other <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners,</hi> whereby often debates with the Refiners and the Gold Wyer-drawers, and Silk-men (when they were there) the said <hi>Commissioners</hi> learned how to draw a <hi>Proclamation, Commission,</hi> and <hi>Instructions,</hi> and the Finers <hi>Indenture of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> all which were suddenly after put in execution; And a <hi>Proclamation bearing date the eighteenth of</hi> January, <hi>in the eleventh yeare of King</hi> Charles was proclaimed by which it was commanded, <hi>That no Finer, Goldsmith, Merchant or others, should thereafter sell any fine Silver, or other Silver, to any person or persons, to be used and imployed, in any of the manufactures before mentioned, other then such as should be allowed by his</hi> Majesties Commissioners; <hi>and that no person or persons, other then such as should be allowed by the said Commissioners should be admitted to make or cause to be made any of the aforesaid</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:172733:11"/>Manufactures, with divers other restrictions mentioned more at large in the said <hi>Proclamation.</hi> And a <hi>Commission</hi> was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise issued on't <hi>upon the six and twentieth day of</hi> January, <hi>in the eleventh year of the said late King,</hi> unto divers Lords <hi>of the Councell,</hi> and the persons before named, <hi>and the Lord Mayor of London, the Masters of the Requests, chief Officers of the Minte,</hi> Sir <hi>William Becher Clark of the Councel,</hi> several <hi>Aldermen of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, John Williams, Esq;</hi> formerly the King's Goldsmith, and others, with power and authority to them or <hi>any four of them,</hi> to see the several clauses mentioned in the said <hi>Proclamation,</hi> and the several Articles of <hi>Instruction,</hi> given under the <hi>signe manuell</hi> of the said <hi>late King, bearing date the nineteenth day of</hi> January, <hi>in the said eleventh year of his Reign,</hi> put in due execution; which instructions did consist of nineteen seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Articles</hi> or Ordinances, for the Regulating of the buying, selling, and working of the said manufactures. And all the said Gold Wyer-drawers and other persons admitted to buy Silver or Gold, for the making of any the said manufactures, were caused to enter into Bond to observe the said particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, mentioned in the said <hi>Proclamation, Orders</hi> and <hi>Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and to pay the duty of <hi>six pence</hi> for every ounce of Silver and Gold that they bought and used in the said manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures. And all the Refiners, being eight in number, who used the Trade of <hi>buying and selling</hi> of Silver as aforesaid, were enjoyned to seal an <hi>Indenture dated the seventh day of</hi> May, <hi>in the twelfth year of the said late King,</hi> which was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto them by the <hi>Kings Attorney General,</hi> conteining divers Covenants and Restraints contrary to the Freedome and Liberty themselves and their predecessors before, and their successors since, did and do enjoy, as <hi>Freemen of the City of London,</hi> and members of the <hi>Company of Goldsmiths.</hi> In which said <hi>Indenture</hi> every of the said Eight Refiners were proportioned, how many <hi>parts</hi> of the whole quantity of Gold and Silver they should <hi>furnish</hi> the <hi>Office</hi> withall, according to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172733:12"/>their apprehensions of their ability, as they gave it in under their hands, and they were enjoyned by the <hi>Covenants</hi> of the said <hi>Indenture,</hi> to <hi>bring all Gold and Silver by them provided for the use of the manufactures, to the place appointed</hi> by the <hi>Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, and there to sell the same, and at no other place; nor to sell to any, but such persons as were allowed by the Commissioners to buy the same, and would pay the duties of six pence the ounce imposed as above said: And all their Silver was to be assayed by such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons as the King should appoint; neither were they to sell the same</hi> but at <hi>such prizes as in the said Indenture was limited and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed;</hi> which was lesse by a <hi>penny</hi> in an ounce at the least, then they constantly sold for at their own houses, when they were at liberty; nor might they refine any <hi>old broken Silver, plate or Bulloign of the Kingdom,</hi> (as formerly it was free for them and their predecessors to do) but to make use of forraigne <hi>Bulloigne onely,</hi> which enforced them to keepe double stocks to buy the same, at such particuler times as the Merchants brought it in at; and further, they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to pay a great rent for the place where the <hi>Office</hi> was kept, and to maintain several Clarks extraordinary for the sale of their Silver and Gold, both which cost them at least three hundred pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> whereas before they bought and sold at their own houses, and thereby saved all that charge. And in the said <hi>Indenture the King granted unto them liberty to fell so much Gold and Silver as would furnish the buyers, to be used in the said manufactures, not exceeding an hundred thousand pounds a year, with a non obstante, the Statute of</hi> 4 <hi>Hen. the seventh, and the Proclamation of tertio Caroli,</hi> and <hi>declared, That during the time of seven years, he would not grant any License to any other person to serve the said manufactures, but unto such as should have served as Apprentices to the said Trade of a Refiner, as the aforesaid Refiners had done.</hi> Which said <hi>Indenture</hi> of <hi>Covenants</hi> wherein every of the said Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172733:13"/>was tied to furnish such parts and proportions as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, continued in force but one yeare and eight months, and then it was furrendred, and every of the said Finers was left at liberty, to sell as much of his own Silver and Gold as he could, to all such persons as were allowed to buy the same, but still under the restraint of the rest of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> before specified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where observe,</hi> That none of the said <hi>Covenants,</hi> nor any other Act of the Refiners, nor any <hi>grant or License from the King to them,</hi> therein contained, did lay any <hi>restraint</hi> upon any <hi>Goldsmith from selling,</hi> or, <hi>Gold Wyerdrawers or others from buying,</hi> any Silver or Gold for the use of the said manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, or any other use, which was lawful for them to do by any <hi>Charter</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> or the Company of Goldsmiths: But what restraint there was it was contained in the <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Commission and instructions,</hi> and the execution thereof, and so was adjudged by the <hi>grand Committee of Parliament;</hi> neither were the Refiners the proposers of them, or any of them, as by an Order of <hi>the King,</hi> and <hi>the Lords of the Councel, dated the eighteenth of March,</hi> 1639. (amongst other things) it did appear, part whereof followeth in these words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172733:14"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="royal_order">
                        <p>
                           <hi>AND whereas it was informed, to his Majesty and the Board, that the Refiners were reported by the Wyerdrawerrs, to have been the proposers to his Majesty of this manner of regulation, for their own private Lucre. It was declared by his Majesty and their Lordships, that the said Regulation was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the Refiners, nor any of them, but originally grew upon the severall Petitions of the Gold wyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawers, who complaining to his Majesty for want of Government in their Trades, made suit to be incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, with tender to his Majesty of One thousand pounds</hi> per annum, <hi>in lieu of his Customes, and two pence</hi> per <hi>ounce, for such forraign Bulloign as should be used by them, over and above the currant price of the Merchants. Nevertheless, his Majesty being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of many falsities practised by the workers in that trade, did not think fit to intrust it in their hands. But after sundry debates and Consultations touching that businesse, his Majesty did direct the same to be managed by</hi> Commission, <hi>according to</hi> instructions, <hi>conceived by advice of his</hi> privy Councel, <hi>and assigned these Refiners for the Refining and selling of all such Gold and Silver as should be used in the said
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172733:15"/>manufactures, by persons allowed to buy and work the same.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>At the making of which Order there was present,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>The Kings Majesty.</signed>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Lord Ar. Bp. of Cant.</item>
                                 <item>Lord Keeper.</item>
                                 <item>Lord Treasurer.</item>
                                 <item>Lord Privy Seal.</item>
                                 <item>Lord Duke of <hi>Lenox.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Lord <hi>Mar. Hamilton.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Earl <hi>Marshall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Lord high Admiral.</item>
                                 <item>Lord Chamberlain.</item>
                                 <item>Earl of Dorset.</item>
                                 <item>Earl of Holland.</item>
                                 <item>Lord <hi>Goring.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Lord <hi>Cottington.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Lord <hi>Newburgh.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Mr. Treasurer.</item>
                                 <item>Mr. <hi>Comptroller.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Mr. Secretary <hi>Windebanke.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172733:16"/>
            <p> And notwithstanding all the Impositions and Burdens laid upon the said Refiners as before is set forth, and there sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission thereunto, there were many endeavours used, and new <hi>propositions</hi> made by some of the Goldwyer-drawers and others, and were much countenanced by some of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners,</hi> to put the Refiners by their <hi>Trades,</hi> and to bring in those that never were Apprentices to the same; nor had skill to Refine Gold and Silver for the service of the said manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures; that thereby the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Gibs</hi> might be prosecuted in the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> upon the aforesaid <hi>Bill,</hi> for doing the <hi>same things</hi> in their former constant course of trading, which now the King had Licensed them to do. The sense and apprehension of which danger, caused the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston,</hi> and <hi>Alderman Gibs,</hi> to sue for their pardons, which they obtained from the <hi>King</hi> by the help and procurement of Sir <hi>William Beecher,</hi> which pardons contained <hi>onely</hi> a discharge from the penalty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in that old <hi>Statute of a Hen. seventh,</hi> for selling of fine Silver and Gold for the use of the manufactures herein mentioned, and for buying and selling of Silver at the prices of the Market, when it was dearer then the price of the <hi>Minte,</hi> which was the constant practice of all persons that either <hi>bought or sold</hi> Silver, and yet was urged against the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston,</hi> and <hi>Alderman Gibs,</hi> to be a breach of the said <hi>Proclamation of</hi> 3 <hi>Caroli;</hi> and in their said par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons because they would not so much as tacitly admit or seem to be guilty of any of the crimes that were so much suggested against them in the said <hi>Bill,</hi> and at the <hi>Councell-Table,</hi> they did particularly cause to be <hi>excepted out of the said pardon, the culling and melting of Silver Moneys, the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting of Gold and Silver out of this Realm, into the parts beyond the Seas, the buying of Plate stolen from the King, or any of his Subjects, or the selling of Counterseit Silver, or other Silver worse
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172733:17"/>in fines then the Standard,</hi> and immediately after these par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons were obtained, there was a cessation of all such <hi>opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> contrived against them as aforesaid, only they continued <hi>under the burden of their Covenants,</hi> untill the beginning of the <hi>Parliament, in Anno</hi> 1640. and then all the Refiners Petitioned against the said <hi>Covenants,</hi> and obtained a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the second cause that was heard, before the <hi>Grand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> in the then <hi>House of Commons;</hi> wherein they set forth how they had been restrained from the free exercise of their Trade, and prosecuted (in an illegal manner) by <hi>S.H.M.</hi> his <hi>Commission,</hi> and by the said <hi>Bill</hi> in the <hi>Star-Chamber.</hi> At which hearing the Gold-Wyer-drawers (who had also Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned against the said Regulation) were fully heard, several dayes by their Councel what they could object against the Refiners and Commissioners, and upon full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration taken of the whole matter, the said <hi>Committee voted</hi> the said <hi>Regulation</hi> to be a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and the Refiners to be free from the <hi>creation and execution thereof,</hi> and so the Refiners and Gold-Wyer-drawers became free to exercise their Trades as formerly; And Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his imployment of melting Gold and Silver that was <hi>coyned</hi> in the <hi>Minte,</hi> without the hearing of any the least complaint made against him to the <hi>King</hi> for so doing, or any examination of any of the Officers of the <hi>Minte</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, much lesse of any anger the <hi>King</hi> should conceive against him, or any <hi>account</hi> that he feared to be called unto for the same, the imployment being indeed as inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as it was esteemed in the eye of the world, which twenty years before he had been intreated to take upon him, by Sir <hi>Edward Villers</hi> then <hi>Master worker</hi> of the moneys, at the Sollicitation of Mr. <hi>Anthony Morley.</hi> And after the said <hi>Sir Edward</hi> left that Office, then by Sir <hi>Randolph Cranfield</hi> the succeeding <hi>Master worker,</hi> both which had an allowance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172733:18"/>from the King of fourteen pence out of every pound weight of coyned moneys, as <hi>Master workers,</hi> and did out of the same make good what the Silver and Gold wasted in melting, and paid the moneyers for coyning, and did contract with and allow the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen graines, which is two pence, upon every pound weight for the waste and charge of melting, during all the time of their continuance in the said Office. And after them the said Office was executed by <hi>Commission</hi> granted to Sir <hi>William Parkhurst,</hi> and the rest of the chief <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Minte</hi> who made the same contract as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly with Sir <hi>John Wollaston.</hi> And after them Sir <hi>Robert Harley</hi> executed the said Office, and continued the said contract for divers years together. And after him Sir <hi>Thomas Aylesbury</hi> and Sir <hi>Ralph Freeman</hi> did execute the said place, by Commission, and they continued the said contract with Sir <hi>John Wollaston.</hi> And after them Sir <hi>Robert Harley</hi> did again execute the said place, and still continued the contract. And after him Dr. <hi>Geurdian</hi> (the present Master worker) came to the said Office and continued the said contract. All which times being reckoned together makes up the number of thirty years and upwards; in many of which yeares the aforesaid allowance of two pence out of every pound weight of Silver did not amount to thirty pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> And the allowance of all the said years being put together doth not amount to above nine hundred twenty six pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> out of which is to be deducted all the Silver wasted in the melting, which men of experience in that businesse do well know, will amount to little lesse then the whole allowance: and add to this, the charge of maintaining such a number of Servants, as were necessary to discharge and perform the labour, skill, and trust, of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172733:19"/>such so painful and hazardous a businesse, besides the making good of all losses happened by casualties, which at some times were very great, and that the said <hi>Master workers and Commissioners</hi> well knew, which made them so desirous from time to time to continue the said con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract; it being lesse then was allowed for waste and melting in the Reign of <hi>King Edward the sixth,</hi> as may be made appear by an account of a <hi>Master worker</hi> in that time. And lesse then was allowed, by one third part, to Mr. <hi>John Lonison, Master worker</hi> in the Reigne of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> as may appear by a demonstration made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lords of the Councill, in Anno</hi> 1577. and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be lesse then was allowed to Mr <hi>Broade</hi> Refiner, predecessor to the said Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> in that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All which being duely considered and defalked, the Remaines will appear to be very little and inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, towards the making of Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> an <hi>Alderman.</hi> By which it appears the Relation concerning this Businesse made by Mr. <hi>Thomas Violet</hi> afore mentioned in a Booke of his lately published, to be as true as that his expression, <hi>What Alderman</hi> Wollaston <hi>hath been to the Government, that makes him uncapable to bear Office in the Common-wealth.</hi> Whereas it is sufficiently known that he still continueth Alderman of <hi>London,</hi> and in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of the Peace, both in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex.</hi> And like unto that scandalous story that in the said Book he patcheth up together, with many false assersions of his own devising, to make it seem the more probable, that Alderman <hi>Gibs</hi> made a contract with Mr. <hi>Emans,</hi> the said Mr. <hi>Violet</hi>'s Master, for thirty thousand pounds of heavy shillings, six pences, and halfe crownes, which the said Mr. <hi>Violet</hi> there saith, he delivered with his owne hand, and contradicteth himselfe in the same
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172733:20"/>Page, saying, that Alderman <hi>Gibbs</hi> would never have these shillings, six pences, and halfe crownes, from Master <hi>Emans</hi> in kind, but the property altered and melted into Ingots without fraud; notwithstanding which bargaine, he put in every Ingot so much Copper which was about a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the ounce, for his Masters profit, at severall times within foure yeares, which Alderman <hi>Gibbs</hi> hath paid for to his the said <hi>Violet</hi>'s Master, after the price of good Silver, as came to above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty poundes <hi>Sterling.</hi> As if he could make the world believe that Alderman <hi>Gibbs</hi> was so ignorant, and carelesse in his profession, as to be so cozened foure yeares together; when as he confesseth in another place of his Booke, that the said Alderman <hi>Gibbs</hi> had a paire of assay Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance in his Closet, whereby he could and did make assayes of his Master <hi>Eman</hi>'s Silver with the Standard piece, and also he and all other Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths might and did commonly make use of the Assay Master at Goldsmiths-Hall, whose Office it was to make assayes upon Oath, without any charge to the owner, which within two houres after it was sent to him, would and commonly did, returne the report under his hand of the true valew to halfe a farthing in every ounce. Which is oftentimes more then the Refiners and Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths gaine by the Silver that they bought and solde one to another. And the manner of this tryall was by a small piece cut off from every Ingot, which contained not the worth of a three pence, and was the constant course of all Refiners
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172733:21"/>and Goldsmiths, that bought and sold one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to bargaine for all Silver that was melted into Ingots, at so much an ounce <hi>Starling,</hi> and to be adjudged of the goodnesse by the assay-Masters report, and accordingly to allow or abate, as it was better or worse manifested by the assay Masters report; and therefore such a bargaine as aforesaid, would have beene uselesse and ridiculous; for by the same reason that he saith the said Alderman was cozened to the value of an hundred and forty poundes, he might have beene cozened five times as much.</p>
            <p>Besides, many other falsities in the said Master <hi>Violet</hi>'s Booke concerning Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> and <hi>Alderman Gibbs</hi> being the projectors and Authours of a Monopoly; and the using all his indeavoures to keepe Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> from being indicted upon high crimes and offences, and making them seeme the oppressors of the rest of their profession, in their shares expressed in the first Indenture, and the Gold-Wyer-drawers in their prizes of Siver, &amp;c. solde to them, and their pressing the Commissionres to cause searches and seizures of such Wyer draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Silver, as did not buy of them, and neither doth nor can instance in any one particular. And the disgracefull tearmes he puts upon them in calling them the Kings sheep-biters, and multitudes of other untruthes within themselves, being compared with what hath beene here truly related, by a person that was perfectly knowing of all the transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the former proceedings, and the testimony of all that know the life and conversation, the faire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172733:22"/>and upright dealing of Sir <hi>John Wollaston</hi> and <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Gibbs,</hi> and the reputation and condition of the said Mr. <hi>Violet,</hi> will neede no further manifestation of their innocency, and of his malice, shewed in his said Booke, then what is herein expressed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172733:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>